On an individual level, I think AI can
be a savior in the sense that I mean
it's never really been easier to start a
business. The cost of doing so, at least
for many of these industries, is lower
than it has been. There are ways to, you
know, get services and stuff like that
at lower cost than there were 5, 10, 20
years ago because AI can really extend
the reach of one person or a small team.
>> We are very fortunate here at Euro
Dollar University to have none other
than Lynn Alden with us to talk about
any number of things here. I think Lynn,
let's let's talk about the stock market
because I think the stock market is on
everybody's mind for good reason. I
really this is one of the reasons I
wanted to have you on. I wanted to get
your take on what's going on with
equities. We hear about everything, you
know, AI bubble, concentration risk.
Should we worry about semiconductors? Is
there a signal there? What do you think
about equities maybe from a broader
perspective and then you maybe drill
down into some more micro scale topics.
>> Yeah, big question. Happy to be here.
It's been a long time since we had a
chat. Yeah, equities obviously is a
super broad topic, you know, kind of a
big focus of mine. You know, I've been
pretty bullish on equities just because
of the fiscal environment that we're in.
Now, obviously there's, you know, there
there are certain areas that are kind of
heated at the moment, but broadly
speaking we look at the US and globally,
you know, most of what we see in the
equity market I would say is backed by
fundamentals, which is that we have
earnings growth, we have revenue growth
for the most part. You know, we
obviously there are pockets of excess,
but in general it's been, you know, most
of the moves have been rational. They
occasionally get ahead of themselves.
There are certainly are risks. So, the
question is how durable are some of
these earnings? I think that that's a
whole another topic. And I mean even
outside of the obvious areas, you know,
the hyper scalers, the semiconductors,
you know, the equity market's not as
strong when you take out the winners,
but, you know, I think that for a quite
a while uh international equities were
basically under owned. There you know,
there was not a lot of reason to have
just kind of excess capital in them. You
know, especially globally mobile capital
was mostly shoved into US. It still is.
So, for some of them that just the
fundamentals stopped working going down.
I mean not many people would have
guessed that, you know, during 2025,
kind of the year of trade wars, that
like Latin American banks would do
amazing, right? It's but it but their
price is though if the world was ending
and then it just didn't. I mean, Brazil
has super high real rates, banks are
priced cheaply, and a number of other
areas, too. Colombian banks, I mean, you
know, there there was like weird pockets
of the market you wouldn't expect it had
like, you know, kind of crypto-like
returns in a year you wouldn't think it.
So, I think there's a ton of places to
look in the equity market. And so, I
don't I don't really treat it as just
one big index, you know, just the Nasdaq
or just the semiconductor ETF or, you
know, just the S&P. But, I think
>> AI or just, you know, everything AI. I
think that's I think maybe, Lynn, that's
part of the problem here is that we hear
only about a specific part of the
market. It's sort of like the smallest
little a minority that uh that's the
loudest. So, maybe our our opinion or
our view of the stock market is clouded
by hyperfocus on one part of the
marketplace. And as you're talking
about, there's there's a whole other
world out there.
>> Yeah, and I mean, so the the the biggest
like in terms of like the combination of
size and performance, you know, it's
it's easy to understand why there's been
so much focus on the AI trade because
even though some pockets of the market
have have done really well, they're
generally smaller parts. So, the
combination of the some of the the
percentage returns that have come from
the AI space combined with the starting
size is truly remarkable. I mean, if you
go back to, I think, you know, late 2022
or so, you know, if you if you kind of
added together the top, call it, 15
semiconductor stocks, you're looking at
something like a two or three trillion
market cap with all of them combined.
And then, you know, you know, some
months ago, I mean, that when I compiled
the data last time, I mean, that that
particular figure was well over 16
trillion, you know? And so, you had both
the obviously a very big percentage gain
in a pretty short period of time, a
handful of years. And then, you had just
the the sheer size of that happening.
And a lot and then, you know, kind of
the blow-off top was that whole period
from, say, autumn of 2025 into June
2026. I I think some of the easier
returns from that trade are are over. I
still think that some semiconductor
names probably have a higher like to go
before, you know, maybe the cycle's
over. I think some of those bottlenecks
still might persist for a period of
time. But then even outside of that
trade, I mean, for example, the equal
weight S&P 500, while that's not been as
high-flying or exciting as some of the
the the more concentrated areas, that's
currently bouncing around all-time
highs. So, it it even that is just
grinding higher and you generally get,
you know, you get more sector fusion,
even though it's the same names as the
the the market cap weighted S&P. You
know, in general, because equal
weighted, you're kind of more slanted
toward the mid-cap side than you are in
the in the more concentrated, you know,
the the market cap version. So, there
are ways to have equity exposure that
don't rely on being concentrated. And,
you know, when when things are great,
you're generally going to be
underperforming, but if you do get kind
of a big correction in some of the
overbought areas, uh you're already more
spread out. So, I think, you know, if
someone's looking at say a passive
portfolio as an example, they have an
equal weight S&P 500 slice and a couple
international slices and then other
asset classes, there's not a lot to do
over time. And and of course, you know,
if they want to be more active, they
want to pick names, if they want to get
to where money's flowing in, they can be
more active.
>> Yeah, so then let's talk about maybe
some emerging cuz I think that's
probably a good segue, right? I mean, if
there is is there a risk to the broader
marketplace? So, if if all the returns
are into this narrow segment, and not
all the returns, you know, I'm being
being oversimplified here. But if a lot
of the returns, a lot of the attention,
a lot of focus is in a narrow segment,
does that potentially lead to, okay, we
get into a cap ex cycle that starts to
run into problems and then roll over,
you know, the AI bust, AI bubble
narrative that's out there. I mean,
there's probably some truth to that.
Does that threaten the overall
marketplace because the overall
marketplace hasn't participated to the
same extent and therefore may not be as
overvalued? Is there a sentimental
channel where everybody just says,
"Screw it, I'm out of stocks entirely."?
Is that the downside risk the entire
marketplace? What are the emerging
things that you look at as so far as,
"Okay, it's been pretty good for the
last couple years. What what could
possibly go wrong here that spoils the
party?
>> Yeah, I think there's a handful of
things and and they're not surprises,
but but trying to get the timing right
is hard. So, one of them would be a more
acute energy shock. You know, a lot of
people are monitoring for risks of that.
And two would be kind of the the
exhaustion, I would put it, of the AI
cycle, at least this this part of the AI
cycle. And, you know, any sort of
technological trend can be early or can
be overdone for periods of time. I mean,
the dot-com bubble is the one everybody
thinks of. And, of course, the irony
with that was that, you know, 10, 15, 20
years later, almost all the things they
expected came true. It's just that it
was it was front-loaded by like 10
years. And and not all the names they
thought would win would be the winners,
and you kind of have that next cycle
come along. And, of course, some of the
same winners like Amazon. And so, I you
know, I I there's a risk somewhat, I
think, of that happening here, which is
you overbuild certain things, you get
too much capacity, you get overbought in
certain areas. And then a lot of the
bullish things come, you know, maybe not
15 years later, maybe 5 years later
even. But, you've already kind of done 5
years of gains in say a a 9-month
period. And so, that's you know, that's
where the risks And, of course, just
like any new trend, there are
unprofitable layers here. So, I mean, on
one, you know, the the kind of the end
of the chain, the semiconductors, for
the most part, they're they're doing
free cash flow growth. So, so money's
pouring in. They are doing CapEx, but
they're making more than they're
investing. So, they're just kind of
they're stacking cash. They're doing
great. Are generally still trading at
kind of pretty benign price-earnings
ratio just because they have a long
history of being cyclical. So, they're
they're kind of priced more like like
commodity names, for example, uh even
though that they've grown to very large
market cap. The hyperscalers are
generally growing without free cash flow
for the first time in a very long time.
I mean, for the longest time, like
throughout the 2010s, early 2020s, these
mega-cap tech companies had really high
ROI growth. And they had no CapEx, they,
you know, they had search, they had kind
of lock-in, you know, like Microsoft
lock-in environments. It was really kind
of like low-friction growth. And so,
they didn't have to you lot of CapEx,
Uh, least relative to their size. I
mean, by by sheer numbers they did a lot
of capex, but as percentage of their
revenue, it was pretty much in check.
And so, they could plow their cash into
share buybacks, some of them into
dividends, and just having a fortress
balance sheet. But now that we're in
more of this hardware era, and AI has
less switching costs, you know, than
than network effects, or you know,
social media networks, or search, or or
operating systems, they're a lot more
competitive. And so, they're plowing
their money into into capex. And so,
they're betting that they won't have to
repeat this too frequently. It it kind
of comes down to the debate of how long
do do some of these investments have?
How how long should the depreciation
cycle of them be before they have to,
you know, replenish their semiconductors
and and things like that. And that's
why, for example, when you look at their
earnings expectations, it's still good,
but their free cash flow dried up
because they're spreading that that
cost, uh, accounting-wise. But then the
question is, does that really
materialize the way they think they
will? That's kind of the big question
mark. And then, of course, above that,
you have full and profitable things,
like the the frontier AI labs, are
running at massive losses, and they're
VC-funded. And that's, you know, the
classic VC bet. And I, you know, I'm not
I'm not an AI VC investor, but I work,
you know, I'm a partner at a VC firm, so
I kind of see this this from multiple
angles. It's natural for them to be
unprofitable because they're kind of
going all in on growth, and and they're
they're betting that the cost come down
as as, you know, the the scale takes
place. You hit a critical mass. So, what
they're kind of expecting is that, you
know, token costs go down over time. You
know, Moore's law keeps kicking in, and
developments keep kicking in, and that
even right now, you know, if someone
pays $200 a month for for AI, for
example, or they're on a different type
of plan where they're kind of paying
more for usage, they're generally
getting subsidized by those VC investors
because they want just more people using
that. They want it to become an integral
part of of work and life. You know, they
want to keep kind of pushing the
frontier forward, and they hope that
that over time the cost will compress,
and that that these, you know, in some
years ahead, this will this will be
somewhat more balanced. The problem is,
you know, any number of things. One is
obviously the rise of open weight models
can challenge in the pricing of these
and they're already even with their
current pricing, they're already deep
underwater. Just overall kind of like
ceilings for how effective AI can be in
the workplace. So for instance,
you know, future quality points. I mean,
that you know, anyone who's used
extensively sees certain benefits and
certain limitations. It's not magic. And
so, you know, you have this kind of
flywheel to the upside, but then it can
it can get exhausted after a period of
time. When VC investors, you know, go
back for another round in some of these
companies or these companies try to go
public and they start to you know, if
some of the numbers start to stagnate
from these open weight models, investors
can say, "Maybe I shouldn't be paying
this multiple of sales or maybe I should
ask more about, you know, what what what
year do you expect you might possibly
start to break even on this." Which
again, I mean, VC companies do run
unprofitably usually, but you know, they
still want to say, "Okay, what is what
is the path here? You know, what does
what does this look like eventually?"
And so, I think that's kind of the the
biggest risk is when does that
exhaustion cycle kick in? I'm I'm
currently I wouldn't invest, for
example, in the frontier labs
themselves. I think that there's very
low switching costs. You know, there's
one that's kind of ahead for period of
time and everybody switches to using
that and then the other one kind of, you
know, locks in and and kind of catches
up and surpasses it and people switch
right back. It's not like an operating
system. It's not like a social network.
People will change tools when one of
them's giving them them more bang for
the buck, which that's a really hard
investing environment, especially when
you have companies priced at, you know,
over a trillion market cap or so in that
such a competitive environment. The
hyperscalers, I think are still a
question mark at the moment. The the
chip stocks, it's consensus, but I don't
I don't I'm not sure that that trade's
over yet just because they they are the
genuine bottlenecks. Generally hard to
build a new foundry. Property there is
really strong. There are, you know, a
lot of good traits there. And so, that
in my opinion mostly becomes an issue of
how much you pay for the risk. If you
think the cycle's another 3 years and
ends up being 1 year, you could get in
trouble. If it ends up being 5 years,
you could, you know, you could get
wildly rewarded. So, I think what when
those consolidate for periods of time,
they're still interesting. But, a lot of
other parts of the market are at risk.
And of course, if those other parts of
the, you know, if eventually the VC
funding dries up, if eventually the
profitability of all things challenged,
they can eventually hit the demand side
of the chip stocks. I just think they I
think they still have probably time to
hit them would be my base case.
>> Yeah, so sort of like juggling tails
here, right? I mean, on one side, like
you're right, there's still an upside
here because, you know, AI is I think we
all agree AI is going to be a potential
game It's not a potential, it's going to
be a game-changing technology. So,
you've got that dangling out there. Even
for the VC firms, you're right. They're
The reason why they're absorbing losses
is because they see massive returns on
the on the upside. And then the downside
is, I think you just hit the nail on the
head. We've all used AI. We know that
it's not quite ready for prime time just
yet. It may be in a couple years, but
it's not there. And so, does that
friction potentially drag on growth and
then lead to the VC stocks first maybe
getting hit and then the frontier model
companies, maybe some of them start to
struggle. And does that does that erode
sentiment in the hyperscalers? And since
the hyperscalers are front and center in
everybody's face on social media and
every other form of media, does that
potentially I think they I think a lot
of people have gotten themselves
resigned to the fact that this looks a
lot like the dot-com era. But, does that
necessarily mean that the rest of the
stock market has the same the same
potential vulnerability? So, let's let's
think about this a little bit from the
perspective, okay, VC the frontier
models get into a little bit of trouble.
Maybe the semiconductor you know, they
start to show some weakness. The
hyperscalers, okay, maybe not
everybody's going to win there. Some of
the cash flow numbers don't make sense.
The debt cycle maybe shifts a little bit
more unfavorably. Does that lead
necessarily to something like, you know,
a full-blown correction or even a
full-blown kind of dot-com crisis
dot-com bubble 2.0 dot-com bust 2.0? Is
there is there really that kind of risk
from what is really a concentrated
sector?
>> My expectation would be less of a total
drawdown risk than the dot-com bubble. I
mean, that you know, with equities
anything's possible. I mean, you know,
they they go up, they go down. Uh my
base case wouldn't be, you know, a 2000
or 2008 type of of massive equity
drawdown. I view a bigger risk of more
of a stagnation, where you have uh
somewhat of a more moderate correction,
and then something like sideways chop as
fundamentals catch up. You know, one of
the kind of instructive things might be
from the dot com bubble uh era, you
know, we we think of the the crazy tech
stocks, but then there are even other
stocks like Coca- Cola or Walmart, that
back in the late '90s, they at they at
their peaks, that both of them were
trading at something like 50 times
earnings, right? And they were they were
both of these kind of blue chip,
non-tech growth stocks. They were doing
well fundamentally, but investors were
paying 50 times earnings. And then what
happened after dot com bubble is not
that Coca-Cola and Walmart went on to
crash, but instead they they basically
just churned sideways for uh depending
on the specific name, like a decade or
more, as basically earnings had to
double just to bring the existing price
down to say 25 times multiple, which is
something more appropriate. And it won't
be you know, Walmart at some point, I
think got all the way down like 15 times
earnings. So you had something you had
something like an earnings triple before
you basically paid for your your prior
50 times earnings multiple, e- even
without the stock going down per se. And
so I think that that I mean, there's
certainly a risk of that type of price
action in some of these names. Uh of
course, individual names can can, you
know, crash pretty hard, and then the
question is what does the index do? In
some of my portfolios, I do use the
equal weight version of this S&P 500
just because it does diffuse that risk a
little bit more. I mean, there's still
plenty of kind of reasonable quality
companies trading at 12, 15, 20, 25
earnings, depending on how you know, how
premium they are, what their balance
sheet looks like, and things like that.
There still are basically reasonably
priced parts of the market. You know,
generally speaking, when when you have
major corrections, they go down in
sympathy with it. You know, you have
broad-based selling, you have
algorithmic selling, you have just
overall kind of capital flows coming
out. But mostly in the dot com bubble,
you'd have kind of the non-excessive
sectors getting hit less. And so it
depends on you know, how how kind of
priced they are. And I think one of the
I think you know, unlike so in the 2000s
and the early 2020s when you when there
was the rise of these mega cap tech
companies, they were the primary
beneficiaries of kind of the whole
mobile internet wave. Like I said
before, a lot of that was high ROI
network effect growth. So a lot of the
market cap consolidated into them. I
think kind of the the good side of of
the of how this resolves is I think
actually a lot of the value of AI is
going to eventually end up in the in the
end users. You know, right now like I
mentioned before, that most AI services
are being underpriced basically due to
that VC subsidy. So companies that are
on the forefront of making use of it are
are basically getting more AI than
they're paying for for the most part. So
they can benefit from that if they're if
they're rationing it well. And then even
when this ends, I mean there there
companies who their their end product is
still very much in demand in a post-AI
world. You know, it's a it's a physical
product. It's you know, it's something
that's kind of AI resistant. While their
back end could still get cost
streamlined opportunities from AI. And
so, you know, that's I think one of the
parts of the market that can do pretty
well is that even if the AI companies
eventually suffer or at least certain
parts of it, some of the end use
companies still might just benefit from
what is basically a technology
deflationary, you know, trend and
benefit. There there are some kind of
early studies that show that that
companies that adopt AI ironically tend
to have faster head count growth than
companies that that are slower to adopt
it. Probably because they're kind of
taking market share. Like there's
they're able to be a little bit more
competitive if they're on top of these
things, if they're if they're using the
technology.
>> the macroeconomic benefit of the story
here? I mean, yeah, set aside the
dystopian nonsense about how you know,
AI's going to eliminate jobs. I mean, if
AI works as it's designed and it's
probably going to over time, it makes
people and companies makes workers and
businesses more productive. And in a
competitive environment, if you're more
productive than your competitor, you can
offer better services at lower prices.
You would think that over time that
would be, as you said, head count
positive. So, contrary to the horror
stories of dystopian future, it's
actually I love that you brought that up
cuz I think it brings in you know, sort
of a real world elite you know, early
stage example of how this can go
positively rather than focusing on so
much of these big time negatives.
>> Yeah, I think a lot of the negative
assumptions come from assuming it's kind
of a zero-sum game. Whereas Yes, yes,
yeah. Where Where as tech shifts, I
mean, obviously they're a disruption.
Anything that moves quickly causes
disruption.
>> Yes, there's winners there's winners and
losers, but the pie expands, you know,
so yes, the losers we all focus on the
losers and we lament the jobs that
disappear, but the the pie expands.
Everything gets better and bigger.
>> Yeah, and I think I mean like the one of
the earliest examples is just basically
when when humans harness hydrocarbons
and made the tractor. You know, before
then like over half of people worked in
farming. It took you know, half the
population to feed the whole population.
And you know, with you know, with a with
a tractor and other kind of automated
tools, you basically 10x or more the
productivity of each farmer. So, it
takes you know, 2% of population to feed
everyone. The other 98% of people can
work in in non-agricultural fields. They
can make new medicines and new
engineering products and be influenced
on social media. Whatever they whatever
the case they're doing. They get
anything out of the farming.
>> And then of course when
>> Yeah, cuz there's high value to that.
>> [laughter]
>> They Yeah, and so, you know, media we
call it. But anyway, then you know, with
obviously the rise of automation, you
know, kind of the you know, the whole IT
wave when when you could replace factory
workers with mostly robots and then a
few factory workers to oversee and fix
the robots when they run into issues,
you basically extend the productivity of
each, you know, worker that still works
in that field. That again freed up
people to do other types of work. And I
think that this is kind of like that for
certain especially certain types of
white collar work. They're just very
kind of intensive desk type work. In
many cases, you can extend the reach of
each person doing that. I mean, an an
accountant using AI can do more
accounting work than an accountant
that's that's not using those types of
tools, for example, or an editor. You
know, you can get all the the proof
reading out of the way with with AI,
kind of like super spell check, and then
you can the parts it benefit from human
judgment can come in, and you can, you
know,
you can do more books or more articles
per unit of time by getting some of the
busywork out of the way. You know, to
steel-man the concern of the bears on
that sense, I think that they would say
that there might be some point in the
future where technology is so good that
there's a certain there's a there's a a
bigger share of the population that
can't contribute in any economically
meaningful way compared to a machine.
So, instead of just moving around what
people do, so instead of just, you know,
getting people off the farms and into
the factories or out of the factories
and into the service sector, that that
at some point this the combination of
either automated tools or robots that
say some percent of population that, you
know, whatever the percentage is now
that's effectively unemployable would be
a larger gap. That that I think is is a
is a genuine longer-term, you know,
social-political concern to be aware of.
I I generally think that that point is
further out, and it's unclear what that
number would look like, you know, when
we've run into certain ceilings. There's
also the fact that technology's often
viewed as kind of linear and smooth, and
really it's it's stepwise. An example I
I like to use is like human effort at
flight. For thousands of years we got
nowhere, then, you know, with with like,
you know, gases like we you know with
with like balloons we got a little bit
of flight, but still really poor. And
then when you when you put together like
basically oil and aluminum, which it
were fairly recent human history, you
know, you go from Wright brothers to man
on the moon in a human lifetime. But
then we kind of hit like a a stall. Like
we we kind of hit, you know, like a lot
of the the low-hanging fruit was picked,
and then you you actually don't get a
lot of rapid improvement anymore in most
types of commercial aviation, you know,
even even more advanced aviation, you
know, a lot of the improvements in
flight, for example, have been in the
electronics of airplanes rather than the
physics of how to fly.
>> And so like better flight rather than
necessarily more types of flight.
>> Yeah, incrementally safer flight.
Ironically, it's like it's like we don't
have the the Concord anymore. You know,
it's like we're trying to reinvent the
the faster than sound commercial flight
that we once briefly had in a sense. So,
we we in some ways we hit hard ceilings.
Otherwise other other areas we just got
incrementally safer. Ironically, people
would say less comfortable in flying
than we were maybe decades ago. But, the
point is we kind of just the
we we put a couple pieces together we
were missing. We had a rapid like
exponential gain in in that area and
then we hit a pretty hard ceiling of
what is just possible until we have some
other breakthrough maybe. And I think AI
can run into that where you put the
pieces together, we hit certain critical
mass thresholds, and then it's like a
handful of years of just absolute
takeoff and disruption and new ways of
doing things. But, then eventually we
hit kind of a either a hard or a soft
ceiling where those tools are out there
now and and they stop kind of rapidly
getting better compared to early phase
of going, you know, to to use the term
zero to one.
>> From October 9th through 12th, I'm
bringing together a group of roughly 40
serious investors and financial
professionals along with some special
guests and friends like Hugh Hendry and
Mike Green, George Gammon, Brent
Johnson, and a couple of other ones
where we're going to spend four days
asking the questions that truly matter.
What happens next? Where are the biggest
risks being mispriced? Where are the
opportunities? [music] What should
change our minds? And how should we
think about positioning around it? This
is not a conference built around
speeches. It's a small room built around
discussion, some disagreement, and
actionable advice. So, if you manage
some meaningful capital or you're
seriously interested in all of these
questions and finding answers to them in
a very small intimate setting, apply
below.
>> Isn't that kind of what happened with
the dot coms, too? You mentioned that
earlier. It was a time time difference,
right? The dot coms was right on well,
mostly right. Mostly right on the nose.
I mean, they described the new economy
future that we actually live in, but it
took a couple, you know, 15 years or so
to get there and a lot of it was it hit
that sort of technological ceiling or
functional ceiling, right? It was in
many ways, especially the e-commerce
e-commerce needed something like the
iPad or the iPhone. Really iPhone which
came along that unlocked e-commerce. So,
is maybe potentially something there for
the AI that, you know, there's some kind
of technology or or, you know, evolution
or innovation that's waiting down the
future that really unlocks the secret of
AI because it kind of plateaus out. But
then thinking that, you know, taking
that a step further into the investment
theme, wouldn't that necessarily then
present you again timing difficulties
and timing challenges? And wouldn't it
be wouldn't it be funny if there is a
possibility where, you know, you have
all these AI stocks that are zooming way
ahead and as you described of say
Coca-Cola and say, you know, Walmart,
rather than having them crash, they kind
of plateau for a while and just kind of
hang out and do nothing while they wait
for, you know, the adoption cycle to
overcome its short-run technological
limitations. We really don't get much of
a downside from AI at all. It's sort of,
you know, as you mentioned this maybe
that more typical model is the
fundamentals underneath the AI the AI
build-out starts to become more and more
realistic. And then you have a very
different future where we're into, you
know, we're past the adoption cycle.
We're actually talking more about
macroeconomics of AI than we are
necessarily investing of AI.
>> That that's really how I view it. I I
think that a lot of low-hanging fruits
already been picked. I mean, when you go
from kind of the semiconductor industry
as a whole being worth under 3 trillion
to, you know, approaching 20 trillion,
you know, like another multiple of that
type, obviously that isn't just you you
don't just grow out of the sky. You hit
a certain percentage of like global GDP
or global assets and you just you you
can only grow so far so fast. Uh so you
start kind of hitting into that wall.
And then it just has to show more
results. I mean, right now if you look
at most macro charts, if someone said,
"When did AI take off?" you wouldn't be
able to like the dates are removed. You
wouldn't be able to point and say, "This
is where it happened." Uh you know, it's
not really showing up in the in the
data. I've seen, you know, the analyst
for Bob Elliott has pointed that out
multiple times. He's kind of like he'll
show a chart and be like, "You know,
where's AI books?" And, you know,
there's there's mixed results to the
extent that it's showing up in business
ROI. Uh like I mentioned the study
before that showed that early adopters
tend to to take market share from slower
adopters. That's that's one pretty
extensive study, but other studies are
showing, you know, when when they kind
of poll companies and say, "You know,
have you seen positive ROI for your AI?"
It's not how are you using AI, but are
you seeing positive ROI.
Um you tend to get more mixed results.
So far, it's been obviously easier to
implement on the individual level
because people can use the tools and the
process that that benefit them, whereas
trying to roll out a system that that,
you know, all employees at a company are
going to use or all employees
>> Is it Is that it? Is just like an
experimental phase where No, but
nobody's really sure how to use it yet,
right? There's no, you know, manual that
you can follow and say, "Okay, this is
how we adopt AI." There's no procedures
that companies follow. Is it Is it
really just on productivity of the
experimental phase, right? And and you
almost have to be unproductive when
you're just kind of throwing everything
against the wall.
>> Yeah, and I think that's that's the
irony. I irony of it cuz people are
still doing their jobs while they have
the second job of learning AI.
Before it actually makes their real job
easier. So yeah, in that gap, it seems
unproductive because they haven't yet
saved time with it, but they have this
extra burden. And, you know, there I
mean, there are you know, there's
ironically there
are consulting companies that are at
risk of being disrupted by AI, but in
the meantime are trying to pivot toward
helping other companies implement AI. So
they're trying to solve that problem of
like every company having to figure it
out on their own to say, "Hey, you know,
we we have AI experts and you know,
we've helped these 10 businesses and we
can help you. You don't have to invent
it from scratch." So there there are
services like that. You know, at the at
I'm a partner at Egodisc Capital, so we
do venture type work and one thing we do
is we get our our portfolio founders of
companies together and we have them talk
to each other and say, "Okay, what are
you finding success in with your AI
implementation in your company? What
frictions are you running into?" And
another person will say, "Well, okay,
here's how we solved those frictions,
but you then they they learn something
from the other founder and you you know,
you get networks of information sharing
as we kind of work through what is a
pretty disruptive period. And other than
that, I think it's just it's it's trying
to invest where the low-hanging fruit
is. I mean, one of the ways I've
expressed the view that the end user
might benefit here is, you know, we
started a private equity company where
we you know, we're looking to buy kind
of low multiple real-world private
businesses, but then be able to bring in
AI talent to figure out, okay, how can
we bring this company from a say a a low
adopter to an early adopter and be on
the right side of that curve that goes
out and takes market share from from
others. So, I think that there are
opportunities out there, but a lot of it
just comes down to basically sharing
information that the companies encounter
at least in ways that are not harmful
for their own types of businesses.
>> Okay, let's switch gears here because
you mentioned something earlier that I
definitely want to talk about and that
is the energy shock. So, set aside AI
technology, all that stuff for for a
moment here. Let's talk pure economics.
And it looks like the energy shock isn't
going to go away anytime soon. At least
that's my my thoughts. Love to get your
thoughts on this as well. So, you got
energy prices really, you know, you look
at crack spreads, diesel going to be an
issue, gasoline prices, we got food
that's potentially a problem moving down
the road, potentially shortages. Where
do you see the energy shock playing out
maybe first for the stock or you know,
either way you want to take it for the
stock market or if you want to talk
about macroeconomy and then the effect
on the stock markets because it I think
the energy shock is going to be here for
quite some time.
>> Yeah, that you mentioned the I think the
key issues which are the crack spreads
and diesel really. You know, the early
on in this crisis, people were worried
about, you know, the the mythical $200
barrel of oil, right? So, what if what
if oil goes 200? And you know,
fortunately, that hasn't happened yet. I
mean, we're pretty far into this issue
and that that hasn't happened. We
haven't you know, we haven't even gotten
like the the 150 level or anything
close. Um but because of the really high
crack spreads, you know, they're you
know,
gasoline and especially diesel are being
priced kind of as though oil is lot
higher than it currently is because I
you know what right now is the what's
proven to be the bottleneck is the
refining capacity. As specific the
combination of refining capacity, some
of it's been outright damaged both in
the Middle East and in in Russia. But
then also even ones that are not
damaged, some of that can't get through
the strait, right? Just like the the oil
itself can't get through the strait,
some of the refined products can't get
through the strait. So both from damage
and from physical bottlenecks, the
refining capacity right now is the
issue. There doesn't seem to be a relief
anywhere in sight. Over the Over a long
enough time frame, obviously more
refiners can be built, pipelines around
bottlenecks can be built at great time
and cost to do so many cases. You can
shift from the sea-seaborne trade to
rail and other other ways of doing
things that generally are higher cost
and more frictions and inefficiencies.
So that's we that's how they take the
edge off over time. You know, the
world's a dynamic system so it adapts to
to major bottlenecks, but those are
frictions. So where this ends up showing
up is obviously diesel used for
everything. It's used for
trans-transporting everything. So then
you end up with higher average inflation
than you'd otherwise have because you
just have this inbuilt friction that
this you know that that things that
would otherwise be benefiting from
technological deflation,
you know, kind of going down from maybe
demographics and other issues. You have
all those things that they but then you
have an actual, you know, kind of energy
bottleneck and refining bottlenecks. You
have just higher diesel prices and then
companies their margins are squeezed so
they have to incrementally raise prices
on the consumers for things that have
nothing to do with energy, you know, a
bag of chips for example, just because
getting that bag of chips to to where
the consumer picks it up has a cost. And
then partially what it contributes to
here is the the K-shaped economy or the
two-speed economy, there's different
names for it, which is especially in the
US right now, if you map out where the
deficits are going, you know, fiscal
deficits, they're going toward the
entitlement programs. It's the generally
the the older demographic that that
that's wealthier. They're going toward
uh know, the medical industry, they're
going to defense industry, which means
these employees are getting paychecks
and their and their contractors are
getting paychecks and they're going out
and spending it into the economy. It's
going into interest expense, which is at
least some pockets of that are
spendable. So, they go out and and can
spend that. I mean, if someone with
their money market fund is is earning
more than it would be in a in a zero
environment, which is it's spendable
money. And so, that money's kind of
pouring out into the economy. On the
other hand, if someone is on the lower
end of the income spectrum, if they're
looking to buy a home for the first time
rather than already having with a
30-year, you know, mortgage locked in,
they're facing a combination of still
high home prices with high mortgage
rates. So, it's increasing out of reach.
They're the ones that get more squeezed
by you know, the chips going up in price
because of high diesel prices at the
store or you know, high beef prices to
use a more nutritious example. But, you
know, basically across the board kind of
prices are are squeezing them. So, both
just filling their own car up, but but
then with more broadly the price of
everything. And so, that that's where
you get this kind of K-shaped economy,
which I I think unfortunately is
probably going to persist for a long
period of time. I think the deficits are
going to continue roughly going where
they're going. I think that obviously,
you know, what happens with the Strait
of Hormuz is anyone's guess months, you
know, out from now, but I think for the
most part the K-shaped economy is set to
continue. And when you circle that back
to investing, it's basically that you
want companies that are on the right
side of either fiscal deficit spending
one way or another. You know,
it sometimes is going directly to those
companies, sometimes it's going to
consumers who buy those types of things.
You know, for example, one of the
reasons I've been at least for a while
somewhat bullish on travel is because on
average older wealthier Americans are
receiving a pretty significant part of
the deficit. They're the ones with
assets, they're the ones with passive
income, they're the ones that have
the time and and money to travel. So,
they're traveling, you know, whereas you
know, stocks that are catering to the
middle end of the kind of income
spectrum are the ones obviously in
general facing headwinds. So, I think
that case of the economy
>> you got to follow the money, right? If
we're talking about, you know, this
K-shaped economy in macroeconomic terms,
so there's positive flows and negative
flows. Like, you know, we tend to think
of the economy as sort of like a big
average where everybody kind of
experiences the average. But, in the,
you know, I I think it was Chris
Martenson that was in Arizona a couple
of weeks ago. He called it the I-shaped
economy, which may be a better uh letter
to use because people who are up here in
the top part of the I are experiencing a
very different life than people down
here at the bottom part of the I. And
so, what you're saying is when you're
thinking about investing in the in the
portfolio construction, follow the
money. There's money up here and there's
money not a lot of money down here, so
you probably want to be up here and and
less exposed down here, right?
>> Uh yeah, I think that's exactly it and
with with the caveat that valuations
matter. So, you want to you want to
follow the money, you just want to be
careful about not overpaying for the
areas that are consensus or or where
money's already going. I mean, there is
a, you know, something can be doing
well, but still be a bad investment if
it's priced at 50 times earnings when it
maybe should be priced at 25 times
earnings. But, yeah, basically I think
that that's the main thing to to be
aware of is to buy things where the
money's going with a a mind toward, you
know, bubble valuations when they when
they pop up and try to avoid the the
most excessive areas.
>> So, is there a potential risk there?
Maybe it's not even in the marketplace.
This is the thing that concerns me the
most. With an I-shaped economy, K-shaped
economy, two-speed economy, whatever
label you want to put on it, maybe
that's not necessarily a threat to the
stock market, the macroeconomic climate,
because it has enough positive
attributes and positive monetary flows
and redistribution where it kind of
keeps everything afloat. But, are you
concerned that maybe the consequences
are beyond the marketplace in the
economy itself, first of all, cuz, you
know, combine that with AI, as you said
before, there's potentially a pool of
labor that is unemployable that might be
get bigger over time. We already know
how hard it is for people in the bottom
part of the economy to get a job,
primarily younger people to begin with,
who have you don't have the ability to
start their career, therefore they're
not investing in their own uh their own
capabilities. They can't buy a house,
which means they're not building wealth
that way. They don't get the 401K. Are
you concerned about the social and
political impacts of the K-shaped
economy just beyond investing where
potentially we go into some pretty
darker pretty dark areas?
>> I am and I've written about this a
handful of times, which is and often I
speak of it more in the in the deficit
in the sense that cuz that's a fueling
factor for the K-shaped economy.
>> Yeah,
people don't get that, right? They they
think you know that there's a lot of a
lot of misconception about the deficit,
but the deficit the government spending
is making things worse, not actually
making things better.
>> Yeah, I mean obviously it depends on the
country in question where it goes, but
yeah, in a general sense at least in the
especially in the current US
environment, I would say the deficit is
fueling the K-shape rather than kind of
combating the K-shape. You know, if you
were talking about kind of maybe
post-World War II spending, that'd be a
different environment than than today's
spending. But basically that today's
spending where it is, for the most part
I would say it's fueling the K-shape.
And the the the challenge here is when
people say, "Well, when will the deficit
or debt matter?" as though as there's
like one mythical moment where the US
misses a bond auction or something like
that. And it's that's not it's more like
that slow bleed of basically unrest,
populism, and everybody kind of feeling
that something's wrong and then not
really knowing what the issue is and
then depending on where they fall on
political spectrum, they point to
different things. And you're after the
global financial crisis, you got the
rise of both Occupy Wall Street on the
left and Tea Party on the right. That
you know, changed over time. On the
right, you got more the MAGA side of
things and on the left you get you have
more I mean like the now you have
Mondani in New York for example. Other
things like that. And I do think that
you get the
kind of a rise of in some cases more
collectivist type of ways of doing
things, whether it's socialism,
communism, whether it's certain types of
fascistic type of kind of tendencies
that rise. And I think that's kind of
the one of the major risks is that when
people perceive that the pie is growing,
there's a little bit more of a tendency
to be harmonious. When they feel the pie
is not growing, um, that's when there's
more or issues. And eventually it can
threaten rule of law, it can threaten,
you know, the the economy itself, it can
it can threaten the attractiveness of
capital assets uh, in countries where
the rule of law is, you know, not that
weaker than it was, you know, 10, 20, 30
years ago. And I think that is a
longer-term danger to to monitor. And
then, uh, obviously anyone who's holding
assets has to be worried about risks of,
obviously on the extreme end you have
something like asset confiscation. On
the other hand, you have kind of a, you
know, kind of targeted types of wealth
taxes that you have to kind of move
around and and you have to you have to
pay attention to maybe jurisdiction more
than you did 20 years ago. And and so it
becomes investing and kind of protecting
wealth becomes bigger than just, you
know, blank sheet of paper, what does
your pie chart portfolio look like? But
it's also, you know, what kind of
safeguards do you have, where are you
deciding to live, where you deciding to,
uh, you know, have assets, uh, you know,
domiciled and and things like that.
>> It's an extreme thing, but it's
imminent, right? I mean, that's it's
happening in places like California,
it's only going to continue. If it
passes in California, you're going to
see it spread to other places around the
world, or other places around the
country, not just uh, you know,
California. But that's I think that's
exactly, you know, the when the pie is
not growing, the easiest thing for a
politician to do is say, "Those guys
that you don't like over there, they're
the reason for it." And so it's very
easy for everybody to become polarized
because simply the pie is not growing,
we all want answers to it. And so then
the question becomes, what the hell do
we do? How do how do we get out of this
mess so that we can move into a
situation where the pie is growing? And
my own view is I think, you know, these
are longer-term cycles and we go through
these periods in history, kind of have
to wait them out. But, uh, do you see
any way for us to at least solve the
macroeconomic problem, the macroeconomic
part of it, so that we can start growing
it? Wouldn't it be funny if AI is the
actual answer here? AI kickstarts the
economy and suddenly solves the K-shape
and that would be the ultimate irony.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, it would. I mean I I think I'm a
view that that there's a time-based
component here that that there's very
few ways to accelerate it on average
that the most likely scenario is it just
it takes time to work through this and
it takes time to work through a
demographic shift, it takes time to work
through kind of a debt cycle. People
have to often try a lot of wrong answers
before they find the right answer.
Uh and so you know I can give you know
kind of list of policy ideas but I just
know ahead of time that they're just not
going to be done, they're not going to
be Yeah,
the the chance to implement them all
correctly enough and getting enough
political consensus to do that is
extremely low, which is why I say
nothing stops this train in terms of the
fiscal deficits. You know, it's like
don't fight kind of momentum. And for
AI, I think that I mean the the the
kicker there is that on an individual
level, I think AI can be a savior in the
sense that I mean it makes us that it's
never really been easier to start a
business, for example. You have you know
the the the the cost of doing so at
least for many of these industries is
lower than it than it has to. I mean you
can do you can there are ways to to you
know, get services and stuff like that
at lower cost than there were 5, 10, 20
years ago because AI can really extend
the reach of one person or a small team.
>> Well, AI can be a small team, right?
It's not just
You know, as a business owner, you've
got an entire you know, suite of AI bots
at your fingertips.
>> Exactly. That's the Yeah, that's what I
mean is that you all these tools extend
what what each kind of living, breathing
person can do because you have all these
all agents and and ways of organizing
things and doing things. And so it
becomes not just you know, who has the
assets and connections to build a
startup business but also just who who
has acquired the know-how and the
ability to use these tools efficiently
versus who is either just technically
unable to use them properly or
culturally resisting using them because
they they they believe they're bad for
one one or more reasons, environmental
or you know, whatever whatever kind of
might be causing that. And then you get
a divide in terms of of kind of early AI
users versus slow like stage AI users
more so than than just other things. And
so I do think that at least on the
individual level, AI can be a powerful
tool.
Uh and you know, I in general any sort
of any anything that's good for
productivity, while not obviously not
uniform because there are winners and
losers like we talked about, but in in
general anything that that kind of adds
net productivity to society for the most
part should benefit society. Anything
that reduces productivity like wars or
bottlenecks and their destruction of
existing facilities that that would
reduce the deficits.
Yeah, and that'll detract from, you
know, societal benefit. And and so
that's kind of the the challenge is that
we have this new productivity unlock. We
don't yet know quite how big it is.
Obviously, you know, the bulls will say
it's huge, bears will say it's all an
illusion. Most most answers are being
somewhere in the middle that, you know,
I'm I'm quite bullish on it, but it's
not magic. And but either way there's
some unlock here. The question is how
unevenly will it be distributed in terms
of, you know, who it helps and hurts, 5
10 years from now, and what impact will
have on the economy. But I think that we
have ways of looking at this. We can
look at, you know, what what did
manufacturing of all of automation of
manufacturing facilities do for the
economy? What did it do for workers?
What did it do for this? You know, we we
saw what globalization did. Obviously,
both pros and cons. We saw what, you
know, bringing hydrocarbons to
agriculture did. You know, we have kind
of historical analogs. None of them are
perfect, but we do have analogs what
happens when you have a technology
unlock that is not evenly distributed in
terms of of users or where it happens or
who it affects. But I think we're in
another era like that.
>> I think, you know, I'm more positive
than I maybe most people are. I'm not
not, you know, hyper positive, not, you
know, singularity type of Elon Musk type
of talk here, but I think that solves a
lot of the issues. You know, you have so
much so much economic power and economic
activity that's concentrated in the top.
That's where a lot of the stagnation's
coming from. You know, economic growth,
historically speaking, is small
businesses that become medium-sized
businesses have become large businesses,
and we just don't have that type of
formation. I think you just I think you
nailed it, Lynn, that when you said that
AI unlocks the ability for people to
start businesses, and the real
disruption is there. The ability to to
introduce some badly needed competition
into a lot of areas we wouldn't even
imagine just yet. If people can imagine
it, create a business, a small business
that challenges the existing orthodoxy,
suddenly you get a whole lot of economic
potential, you pile on productivity. You
can see a wave of prosperity in the
future where not only are the benefits
at least somewhat shared. Maybe we go to
a four-day week work week, a three-day
work week. We've got lots of business
There is definitely a positive way
forward here. But, I do want to ask you
We can continue to talk about AI and,
you know, long-term macroeconomic
trends, but I do want to ask you before
we go here, your thoughts on Bitcoin.
Are we seeing another kind of head fake
in Bitcoin? Is there another leg lower
there? Because I would kind of hope that
there is a leg lower. I really want to
buy Bitcoin around 20,000 per coin. But,
what do you see as far as Bitcoin? Has
it Has it been Has it endured enough of
a winter that consolidation We're
getting more signs of buyers entering
the marketplace. So, what's going on
there?
>> Yeah, good question. So, my my guess,
and I don't know, is my guess is that
the bottom's in. The way that I've been
phrasing it before this recent jump
from, you know, the the lower 60s all
the way up to the the upper 70s, is that
I was hesitant to try to I don't find a
lot of value trying to call a precise
bottom. It's more like trying to figure
out are you in a bottoming range or the
opposite? And so, for example, when it
was in the lower 60s for a while after
it kind of hit that capitulation back in
February, my base case was the bottom is
kind of roughly in. Uh we ended up
getting slight invalidation. We we we,
you know, went down to kind of the 58K
level briefly, but not way lower. And
so, my view was, look, okay, we got a
slightly lower low. I still think,
roughly speaking, we're in kind of a
bottoming range. I would be kind of the
level that I would find truly surprising
would be if we do break kind of below
the 50K level on a sustained basis. I
think kind of the the the 50s and in
lower 60s or there's a lot of support
there in terms of we look at on-chain
indicators. We basically have a somewhat
of a different set of indicators for for
Bitcoin than just stocks, for example.
We have all this all the normal charts
that people look at, but then we have
on-chain data and you can see things
like, you know, at what price levels did
a ton of coins change hands? Not just on
exchanges, but literally just
physically, you know, go from address to
address. And there's a lot of support in
that kind of the the 50s and and the low
60s. I I think that the MicroStrategy
issue's been taken off the table for a
period of time. There's a period there
where they had, say, six months of
dollar reserves and and, you know,
otherwise, uh, you might be start
selling a lot of Bitcoin to fund their
liabilities. Now they've kind of
front-loaded that. So, they already kind
of diluted. They already, uh, sold some
coins. And now they have, you know, a
two and a half year plus dollar reserve
to cover all of their, you know,
preferred dividends, you know, for two
and a half years, even if they never
sell another coin. So, I think a a lot
of that kind of overhang has been, at
least, for for, you know, this this this
calendar year next calendar year kind of
taken off the table, uh, as kind of
force sellers. And so, I think actually
the Bitcoin place is in a pretty decent,
um, trajectory here. I'm not one of
those people that thinks, you know, two
months from now we're at all-time highs,
you know, it's kind of the the
periwinkles. Uh, I think it could take
time. I think we could, you know, we
could go back down to the 60s and chop
for for a period of time. But in
general, I do think that the the 60s and
70s are in accumulation zone. That if
someone is bullish on the asset, that
looking back two or three years from
now, this is probably a good entry
point. But, you know, it it's, you know,
I I I think that it's I think it's a a
more mature asset now. It's more liquid
asset now. Yeah, I think this drawdown
was smaller than prior cycle drawdowns,
but that was after the fact that the the
bull market was smaller than than prior
bull markets. And I think that's
probably the trend to expect now that,
you know, we have ETFs in the market. We
have treasury companies in the market.
It's in general just a larger, more
liquid market. And so, I I my current
view is I'm I'm kind of structurally
bearish on a lot of several parts of the
digital asset space. I think a lot of
that ran its course and it was kind of a
zero rate phenomenon. Uh but I do think
that Bitcoin and I do think that stable
coins still have a long runway of growth
ahead. It was obviously Bitcoin being
the more investable volatile part of
that and stable coins being, you know,
there there are some ways to invest but
for the most part that's more of a macro
story, I think. Whereas Bitcoin is more
of an investor story.
>> So if Bitcoin is a more mature market,
maybe it doesn't have as much beta and
therefore that actually would help out a
lot because beta is one of the biggest
drawdowns to it or biggest uh drawbacks
to it. So wouldn't that be funny, too?
Well, Lynn, I really appreciate your
time uh taking time to talk about it,
you know, so much here with the stock
market, AI. We we kind of hit a lot of
topics. Uh really appreciate everything
that you all the insights that you
shared. I was going to say, you know, in
this part of the interview I would say,
you know, where Lynn, where can
everybody find you? But if you don't
know where to find Lynn Alden, I can't
help you out. It's very easy to find.
Just Google Lynn Alden, you'll find her.
Tremendous amount of insight and
research. Uh so again, thank you for
your time and stopping by for here at
Eurodel University.
>> I appreciate that. Thank you for having
me on.
>> Take care, Lynn. One thing I really care
about with Eurodel University Live is
not the speakers. I mean, we like the
speakers. [music] But what we really
care about is the people who are in that
room. And especially the people who are
sitting next to you as much as who might
be speaking at any given time. There are
only going to be 40 people there and I
want them to be people who are managing
real capital, running real businesses,
making real investment decisions, and
who actually have something to
contribute to the conversation. [music]
Because over four days, a lot of the
value isn't going to come from me
standing up and talking and doing
PowerPoint presentations. [music]
It's going to come over intimate
dinners, in the small groups, in the
questions that somebody asked that you
hadn't thought of, or meeting somebody
who looks at the same problem [music]
completely differently than you do, and
might actually come to similar
conclusions. That's why we're not just
putting out a checkout page. We're
talking to everyone before they come in.
We want to build a room where you can
sit down next to anyone who's there and
know that you're going to have a
conversation that's worth having. If
that sounds like the kind of room you
want to be a part of, apply below.